A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Program Files (Non-Grant), RG 5 FA1799
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Program Files (Non-Grant), RG 5
1975-2019
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation
FA1799
68.4 Cubic Feet (190 containers)
84.3 Megabytes
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
The Program Files, Record Group 5, describe the activities of each of the four program areas, Journalism, Education, Arts and Culture and Community Initiatives. They contain the correspondence and subject files of their officers, and documents which trace the origins and progress of the various initiatives which distinguish Knight Foundation in areas such as undergraduate education, the development of community foundations, minority and mid-career journalism education, museum loan networking, literacy, immunization, and the development of symphony orchestras, etc. The Strategic Planning records provide insight into how the Foundation sought to deal with its growth and create a plan for its future. The Foundation's 2000 reorganization resulted in reorganizing the Program areas into the Community Partners Program, the establishment of the National Venture Fund, and the reaffirmation of the Journalism program. Also included are Endowment files from 1987 through 2004.
Arrangement
This record group is arranged as follows:
Sub-Group 1: Community Advisors
Sub-Group 2: Endowment Files
Sub-Group 4: Manuals
Sub-Group 5: Meetings
Sub-Group 6: Program-Related Files
Sub-Group 7: Program-Related Investment Files
Other Finding Aids
The finding aid for Sub-group 4: Grant Files can be found in FA1795, FA1783 (A-K), FA1790 (L-Z).
- Community Advisors, 1986-2008; 1; 5.51 Cubic Feet 14 letter document boxes, 1 half-letter box
  - Correspondence, 1986-2003; 1; 4.94 Cubic Feet 13 letter document boxes
    Scope and Contents
    The correspondence in these files is from Cities Program Directors James Spaniolo, and Linda Raybin. It contains information about the grant guidelines for each city from 1992-1995, the grant money available for that city, and the status of that city's grant proposals. The general correspondence begins in 1986, and addresses all communities in general.
    Arrangement
    The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the name of the city. General correspondence, sent to all cities, is filed separately. This series is filed chronologically.
    - Aberdeen, SD, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
      General
      Knight File Number - 288
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo to Aberdeen advisors Harold Higgins and Craig Wells, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Aberdeen, grant money available, and status of Aberdeen grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Akron, OH, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
      Knight File Number - 293
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Akron advisors Christopher Harte and John Dotson, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Akron, grant money available, and status of Akron grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Biloxi, MS, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
      Knight File Number - 296
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Biloxi advisor Roland Weeks, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Biloxi, grant money available, and status of Biloxi grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Boca Raton, FL, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13-16)
      Knight File Number - 297
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Boca Raton advisors Clement C. Winke and Roger Coover, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Boca Raton, grant money available, and status of Boca Raton grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Boulder, CO, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 17-20)
      Knight File Number - 298
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Boulder advisors John Dotson and Harold Higgins, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Boulder, grant money available, and status of Boulder grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Bradenton, FL, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
      Knight File Number - 299
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Bradenton advisor Dorothy Ridings, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Bradenton, grant money available, and status of Bradenton grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Charlotte, NC, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
      Knight File Number - 300
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Charlotte advisor Rolfe Neill 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Charlotte, grant money available, and status of Charlotte grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Columbia, SC, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 9-12)
      Knight File Number - 301
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Columbia advisor Frank McComas, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Columbia, grant money available, and status of Columbia grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Columbus, GA, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 13-16)
      Knight File Number - 302
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Columbus advisors Billy Watson and John Greenman, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Columbus, grant money available, and status of Columbus grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Detroit, MI, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
      Knight File Number - 303
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Detroit advisor Neal Shine, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Detroit, grant money available, and status of Detroit grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Duluth, MN, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
      Knight File Number - 304
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Duluth advisor Jim Gels, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Duluth, grant money available, and status of Duluth grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Fort Wayne, IN, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 9-12)
      Knight File Number - 305
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Fort Wayne advisors Richard Sadowski and Scott McGehee, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Fort Wayne, grant money available, and status of Fort Wayne grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Gary, IN, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 13-17)
      Knight File Number - 306
      Correspondence from Creed Black, Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Gary advisor Fred Mott, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Gary, grant money available, and status of Gary grant proposals. 5 file folders.
    - Grand Forks, ND, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 18-21)
      Knight File Number - 307
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Grand Forks advisors Michael Maidenberg and Michael Jacobs, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Grand Forks, grant money available, and status of Grand Forks grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Lexington, KY, 1992-1995 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
      Knight File Number - 308
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Lexington advisor Lewis Owens, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Lexington, grant money available, and status of Lexington grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Long Beach, CA, 1992-1995 (Box 4, Folder 5-8)
      Knight File Number - 309
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to Long Beach advisors Peter Ridder and Richard Sadowski, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Long Beach, grant money available, and status of Long Beach grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Macon, GA, 1990-1995 (Box 4, Folder 9-14)
      Knight File Number - 310
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo, Penny McPhee and Linda Raybin to Macon advisor Ed Olson, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Macon, grant money available, and status of Macon grant proposals. 6 file folders.
    - Miami, FL, 1992-1995 (Box 4, Folder 15-17, Box 5, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 311
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo, and Linda Raybin to Miami advisor David Lawrence, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Miami, grant money available, and status of Miami grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Milledgeville, GA, 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 2-5)
      Knight File Number - 312
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo, and Linda Raybin to Milledgeville advisors Roger Coover, Cecil Bentley, Susan Patterson, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Milledgeville, grant money available, and status of Milledgeville grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Myrtle Beach, SC, 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 6-9)
      Knight File Number - 313
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo, and Linda Raybin to Myrtle Beach advisor J. Michael Pate, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Myrtle Beach, grant money available, and status of Myrtle Beach grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Philadelphia, PA, 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 10-13)
      Knight File Number - 314
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo, and Linda Raybin to Philadelphia advisor Robert Hall, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Philadelphia, grant money available, and status of Philadelphia grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - San Jose, CA, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
      Knight File Number - 315
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo, and Linda Raybin to San Jose advisors Larry Jinks and Jay Harris, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for San Jose, grant money available, and status of San Jose grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - St. Paul, MN, 1991-1995 (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
      Knight File Number - 316
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo, and Linda Raybin to St. Paul advisors Mary Junck and Peter Ridder, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for St. Paul, grant money available, and status of St. Paul grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - State College, PA, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 9-12)
      Knight File Number - 317
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo, and Linda Raybin to State College advisor James Moss, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for State College, grant money available, and status of State College grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Tallahassee, FL, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 13-16)
      Knight File Number - 318
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo, and Linda Raybin to Tallahassee advisor J. Carroll Dadisman, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Tallahassee, grant money available, and status of Tallahassee grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Wichita, KS, 1992-1995 (Box 6, Folder 17-20)
      Knight File Number - 319
      Correspondence from Jim Spaniolo, and Linda Raybin to Wichita advisor Reid Ashe, 1992-1995 re: grant guidelines for Wichita, grant money available, and status of Wichita grant proposals. 4 file folders.
    - Confidential Guidelines for Internal Use, 1986 March 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 320
      Guidelines re: types of grants KF advisors should recommend/reject. Written for Knight-Ridder executives acting as community advisors.
    - General Correspondence, 1990 March 2-1990 March 27 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 321
      Memos to Community Advisors from Creed Black re: effective uses of Cities Program money, separateness of Knight Foundation from Knight-Ridder, List of Community Advisors.
    - General Correspondence, 1991 January 1-December 31 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 322
      Memos to Community Advisors re: Knight Foundation's history and growth, separateness of KF from Knight-Ridder, materials from strategic planning meeting for Cities Program (including remarks by Rolfe Neill).
    - General Correspondence, 1992 November 6 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 323
      Memo to Community Advisors from Creed Black re: misunderstandings of role of community advisors in making grants in their cities, List of Community Advisors.
    - "An Overview of Knight Foundation Cities", 1995 July-August (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 324
      Collection of letters written by Community Advisors in all Knight cities re: overiew of their communities and the process used in reviewing grant requests for the Foundation.
    - General Correspondence, 1994 February 17-May 13 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 325
      Memos to Community Advisors from Creed Black re: materials attached for advisors meeting, memo from Rolfe Neill re: role and responsibilities of Community Advisors.
    - General Correspondence, 1995 December 11 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 326
      Memo to Community Advisors from Creed Black re: National Community Development Initiative (attachments missing), List of Community Advisors.
    - "Grant Effectiveness and Priority Areas of Interest", 1995 July-August (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
      Knight File Number - 4642
      Collection of letters written by Community Advisors in all Knight cities re: identifying the three most and three least effective grants in their communities from 1992-1994 and whether the seven priority areas of interest were appropriate to their communities.
    - General Correspondence, 1996 January 8-December 12 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 3898
      Memo to Community Advisors from Creed Black re: Youth Initiatives and also congratulatory letters to new Knight Ridder publishers.
    - General Correspondence, 1997 July 25-September 24 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 3899
      Includes memos re: the KF trustee decision on establishing the KF communities despite Knight Ridder corporate decisions with its newspapers.
    - General Correspondence, 1998 January 5-1998 November 16 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 3900
      Includes memos re: staff changes at Knight Ridder which would affect the community advisors for KF, feedback from site visits by KF trustees and responses to a request by Hodding Carter for opinions on KF's adopting a biannual grant review cycle and for confirmation on preferred geographic boundaries for grant making.
    - General Correspondence, 1999 January 18-October 15 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 3901
      Includes memos re: a request for additional KF funding for Miami by the Miami Herald, a list of advisors as of September 1999, a note from Peter Ridder objecting to use of KF funds for operating expenses, and a series of memos to the Board of Trustees on funding recommendations.
    - General, 2000 January 15 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 3902
      List of community advisors as of January 2000; and four memos soliciting comments from advisers on several grant requests.
    - Aberdeen, SD, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4167
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, and status of grant proposals.
    - Akron, OH, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4168
    - Biloxi, MS, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 4169
    - Boca Raton, FL, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 4170
    - Boulder, CO, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 4171
    - Bradenton, FL, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 4172
    - Charlotte, NC, 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 4173
    - Contra Costa, CA, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4174
    - Columbus, GA, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4176
    - Columbia, SC, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 4175
    - Detroit, MI, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 4177
    - Duluth, MN, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 4178
    - Ft. Wayne, IN, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 4179
    - Gary, IN, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 4180
    - Grand Forks, ND, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 4181
    - Lexington, KY, 1996-1998 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4182
    - Long Beach, CA, 1996-1998 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4183
    - Macon, GA, 1996-1998 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 4184
    - Miami, FL, 1996-1998 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
      Knight File Number - 4185
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, Jim Spaniolo and Linda Raybin to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, and status of grant proposals. 2 folders
    - Milledgeville, GA, 1996-1998 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 4186
    - Myrtle Beach, SC, 1996-1998 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4187
    - Philadelphia, PA, 1996-1998 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
      Knight File Number - 4188
    - San Jose, CA, 1996-1998 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 4189
    - St. Paul, MN, 1996-1998 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 4190
    - State College, PA, 1996-1998 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 4191
    - Tallahassee, FL, 1996-1998 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4192
    - Wichita, KS, 1996-1998 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4193
    - Aberdeen, SD, 1999 January 22-2000 June 19 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 4266
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, Rick Love and Linda Raybin to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Akron, OH, 1999 January 22-2000 June 13 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 4267
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, Suzette Prude (Harvey) and Linda Raybin to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Biloxi, MS, 1999 January 22-2000 December 12 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 4268
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, and Linda Raybin to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Boca Raton, FL, 1999 December 9-2000 June 15 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 4269
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Boulder, CO, 1999 December 9-2000 December 12 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 4270
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee and Linda Raybin, to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Bradenton, FL, 1999 January 22-2000 June 15 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 4271
    - Charlotte, NC, 1999 January 22-2000 August 30 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 4272
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, Julia Van and Linda Raybin, to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Columbia, SC, 1999 January 22-2000 June 15 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 4273
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, and Linda Raybin, to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Columbus, GA, 1999 January 22-2000 June 15 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 4274
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, Suzette Prude (Harvey) and Linda Raybin, to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Contra Costa, CA, 1999 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 4275
      Contra Costa Guideline Summary, 1999-2001
    - Detroit, MI, 1999 January 22-2000 December 8 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 4276
    - Duluth, MN, 1999 January 22-2000 June 15 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 4277
    - Ft. Wayne, IN, 1999 January 22-2000 June 15 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4278
    - Gary, IN, 1999-2000 January 14 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4279
      Memo (and attachment) from Penny McPhee, to the community advisor re: geographic eligibility and the 2000 guideline and the guideline summary for 1999-2000.
    - Grand Forks, ND, 1999 January 22-2003 December 4 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 4280
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, and Linda Raybin, to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions. Also included are a letter to Mike Maidenberg from Hodding Carter outlining his duties as chairman of the Grand Forks CAC; CAC meeting agenda and notes, August 29, 2001; CAC meeting agenda and notes, April 10, 2003; table of KF investments in Grand Forks, 4/2003; CAC meeting minutes, September 19, 2003; Grand Forks funding guidelines, December 4, 2003 and a table of priorities, outcome, target populations and activities.
    - Lexington, KY, 1999 January 22-2000 December 18 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 4281
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, Rick Love, and Linda Raybin, to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Long Beach, CA, 1999 January 22-2000 August 28 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 4282
    - Macon, GA, 1999 January 22-2000 July 13 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 4283
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, Bryan McCullar, and Linda Raybin, to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Miami, FL, 1999 January 7-2000 December 22 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 4284
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee, Suzette Prude (Harvey), Alfredo Cruz, Rick Love, and Linda Raybin, to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Milledgeville, GA, 1999 December 9-2000 June 15 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 4285
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Myrtle Beach, SC, 1999 January 22-2000 September 12 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 4286
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee. Julia Van and Linda Raybin to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - Philadelphia, PA, 1999 January 22-2000 June 15 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 4287
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee. Rick Love and Linda Raybin to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - St. Paul, MN, 1999 January 22-2000 June 15 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 4288
      Memos (and attachments) from Penny McPhee. and Linda Raybin to the community advisor re: grant guidelines, grant money available, proposals pending, status of grant proposals and Board actions.
    - San Jose, CA, 1999-2000, 1999 January 7-2000 September 15 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 4289